Okay, boker tov.
Today's דף daf is זיין zayin and we pick up with the
very first line on דף זיין עמוד א'. daf zayin amud aleph.
Look at that, רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. So we are
continuing the discussion of what you can do on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed relating to fields and whether it is a דבר האבד davar
ha-aved or not, so there's going to be an actual law. And
we have the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the... I'm
sorry. So yes, so we had recently just read the משנה, mishna,
not about actually working the fields, but about trapping animals, moles and
weasels and rats and so on, which on שביעית shevi'is it's hard
to understand exactly what the problem is because you're not working the
land. But on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you're still doing work, you're
still doing labor. And again the question is, you know, is this
ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos or is this as the גמרא'ס Gemara's been
framing it more in terms of טרחה, tircha, but obviously it's a
much broader category. So now we have the position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה mishna that said you can trap capture
the least... lay traps and capture these animals. Let's take a look.
רבי יהודה אומר משדה האילן כדרכו, Rabbi Yehuda omer mistei ha-ilan kedarko,
in a normal way in an orchard, ומשדה הלבן umistei ha-lavan but
in a wheat field, שלא כדרכו, shelo kedarko, you cannot do it
in the normal way because presumably it's not that much of a
הפסד. hefseid. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, כיצד כדרכו, keitzad kedarko, what's a
normal way of capturing these animals, laying traps for these animals? חופר
גומא ותולה בה מצודה, Chofer guma vetoleh ba metzuda, he makes a
hole and you put the trap in the hole. כיצד שלא כדרכו,
keitzad shelo kedarko, what's the not normal way of doing it? נועץ
שיפוד ומכה בקורדם, No'etz shipud umakkeh bekurdam, you put in a spike
and you bang it with a hammer,
ומרדד umeraded or some have ומרדד האדמה מתחתיה, umeraded ha-adamah mitachteiha, so
you pound down the land underneath it, or I think it could
mean that you cause tremors in the earth around it and the
tremors scare away the animals, scare away the you know the subterranean
pests. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it's taught in a ברייתא,
beraita, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov or רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, כשאמרו בשדה הלבן שלא
כדרכו, keshe-amru bister ha-lavan shelo kedarko, when they said in a wheat
field you had to do it in an in an not normal
way, לא אמרו אלא בשדה הלבן הסמוכה לעיר. lo amru ela bistei
ha-lavan hasemucha le-ir. That's only one that is near the city, so
presumably if it's near to the city, I don't know there's fewer
of these animals and certainly there's not other types of concerns that
if the animals are in the wheat field they'll go somewhere else.
אבל בשדה הלבן הסמוכה לשדה אילן, Aval bistei ha-lavan hasemucha lesdei ilan,
but if it is a wheat field near an orchard,
אפילו כדרכו, afilu kedarko, you can do it the normal way, שמא
יצאו משדה הלבן ויחריבו את האילנות, shema yeitz'u mistei ha-lavan veyachrivu es
ha-ilanos, and this makes it clear why the orchard is a bigger
concern, the phrase ויחריבו, veyachrivu, they'll destroy the trees. So these are
things which really would be destructive if they got into a orchard.
So therefore if there's a wheat field that will... is near an
orchard, you can do what you need to do in the wheat
field. Okay, so that's that. ומקין את הפרץ במועד, Umakin es haperetz
bamoed, you can also wall a breach in the wall, you can
fill in a breach in the wall on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
and then the end of the משנה mishna is ובשביעית בונה כדרכו,
uvashevi'is boneh kedarko, build a normal way on שמיטה, shemita, and again
question is what's even the חידוש chiddush by שמיטה shemita since you're
not working the land at all, you're just making a fence around
the land, that we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. But let's first
look at the filling of the breach on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
כיצד מקין, keitzad makin, how do you fill in the wall of
the breach? So רב יוסף אמר בהוצא ודפנא, Rav Yosef amar behutza
vedafna, in like twigs and reeds, some type of a temporary source.
במתניתא תנן, Bematnisa tanan, in a ברייתא beraita we taught you could
do something even more, צר בצרור, tzar betzror, you can actually put
rocks into that breach in the wall or in the fence, ואינו
טח בטיט, ve'eino tach batid, you sort of like lay the bricks
but don't plaster it over. So you don't make it permanent but
you could certainly make it more sturdy. All right, and again one
could imagine as the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that
there are multiple reasons you would be doing this. Most obvious in
this context is to protect the field from having animals, maybe from
people but animals go through it, you know rabbits and other types
of things and eat the produce or trample it and so on.
But in a different context when you're not dealing with a field
but a yard there could be issues of privacy and the גמרא
Gemara now turns its attention to that. So let's take a look.
אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, לא שנו אלא כותל הגינה. lo shanu ela
kotel haginah. That's only a wall of a garden, like a vegetable
garden so you want to keep out the rabbits.
אבל כותל החצר בונה כדרכו, Aval kotel hachatzer boneh kedarko, but if
you've got a wall around your yard, your backyard, that you can
rebuild the normal way. Now why? You might say oh there's no
vegetables, there's no food for it
to... there's not... they're not going to be destroying any of the
produce. So the most obvious thing that would occur to me would
be the issue of privacy, and anybody knows at the beginning of
בבא בתרא Bava Batra whole discussions about... walls and the rights of
privacy and so on. But the רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom here says,
about eight lines down in the narrow lines, בונה כדרכו דעיקר פסידא
יתירא אי אייל בי גנבי וגנבי ממונא. Boneh kedarko de'ikar pesida yeseira
ei ayyel bei ganavei veganavei mamona. So there you're afraid of protecting
the house from possible robbers, so it's just that's the protection. I'll
get back to that in a minute. So if it's around the
yard, you can do it the normal way. Okay.
לימא מסייע ליה, Lema misayei lei, let's try to bring a proof
to this that our משנה's Mishnah only talking about a garden, but
if it's talking about your own like front yard or backyard, you
have you can even do it from the outset. So לימא מסייע
ליה, Lema misayei lei, כותל החצר
בונה כדרכו. Kotel hachatzar boneh kedarko. Sorry, did I skip a line?
I skipped a line. לימא מסייע ליה, Lema misayei lei, where am
I? Oh, כותל הגוחה לרשות הרבים. Kotel hagocher lereshut harabim. We have
a ברייתא, Braita, תוספתא, Tosefta, that says if you have a wall
that is leaning over into the רשות הרבים reshut harabim and therefore
you're afraid at any moment it might collapse, סותר ובונה כדרכו. soter
uboneh kedarko. You can knock it down and rebuild from the outset,
you know, normally, you don't have to just fill up a gap,
knock the whole thing down and rebuild it. מפני הסכנה, Mipnei hasakana,
in order to protect people from the danger. So we're bracketing for
a moment the knocking down, which is protecting them from the danger,
and we're pointing to the fact that you can build it normally.
So and why? And we're assuming because it is if it's going
right by the
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, it's not your wheat field, it's your yard
of your house. So you see we're dealing with a yard of
a house and you see that you can build it in the
normal way. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. התם קתני טעמא מפני
הסכנה. Hatam katani taama mipnei hasakana. There the reason we let you
build it normally was because we had to let you do the
whole thing because of the סכנה. sakana. So since we're telling you
to knock it down, we're going to let you build it up
normally. But if it was just a normal issue for not a
סכנה, sakana, but just like a breach in the wall, then even
in your yard we would not let you do it normally, we
would have to do it in a more temporary way. So now
the גמרא Gemara tries from the opposite angle. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri,
some try to sort of test what's the question? תא שמע, Tashma,
come and hear, כותל הגוחה לרשות הרבים. kotel hagocher lereshut harabim.
You have a wall of your yard that's leaning into רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. סותר ובונה כדרכו. Soter uboneh kedarko.
You knock it down and you rebuild it normally מפני הסכנה. mipnei
hasakana. Now, because of the סכנה, sakana, so the question is, מפני
הסכנה mipnei hasakana justifies just the knocking down or even the building
up? So here the גמרא's Gemara going to start with what it
ended right a minute ago. That מפני הסכנה mipnei hasakana justifies the
whole thing. טעמא, Taima, says the גמרא, Gemara, מפני הסכנה אין שלא
מפני הסכנה לא. mipnei hasakana in, shelo mipnei hasakana lo. So the
whole thing is only allowed because of the סכנה. sakana. Without the
סכנה sakana you couldn't do anything, you couldn't knock it down and
you couldn't build it up. Don't you see? So you see it's
only because of סכנה. sakana. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב חסדא, Lema teivei
tyufta de'rav chisda, let this be a contradiction of רב חסדא Rav
Chisda who lets you always build the wall of a yard normally.
אמר לך רב חסדא, Amar lach Rav Chisda, no, רב חסדא Rav
Chisda would respond to you, התם סותר ובונה הכא בונה ולא סותר.
hatam soter uboneh hacha boneh velo soter. So no, there the סכנה
sakana justification was only needed for the knocking down part. So the
knocking down you had to do because of סכנה, sakana, and therefore
you would build it up afterwards. But if you just want to
build it, there's a breach in the wall, you didn't make the
breach, it just happened, and now you want to build it, that
you could do the normal way if it's in your yard. The
limitations of doing it not normal are in the field, but if
it's in your yard you're okay. סכנה Sakana is only needed here
to justify the סותר soter part. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
התם סותר ובונה הכא בונה ולא סותר. hatam soter uboneh hacha boneh
velo soter. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכא נמי, hacha nami, the גמרא Gemara asks a pretty like a
question that has a pretty obvious answer. התם נמי, Hatam nami, one
minute, if there's only because of סכנה, sakana, נסתור ולא לבני, nistair
velo livnei, why does it say knock it down and build it
up? Why don't we just tell the guy knock it down? Okay?
Now of course רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say, okay, but you're
allowed to build it up. But if you think that there's some
hesitations in building it up, it's also asking why do we give
special allowance to build it up the normal way if you don't
agree with רב חסדא? Rav Chisda? So the גמרא Gemara says, אם
כן מימנע ולא סותר. im ken nimna velo soter. The obvious answer.
If you tell the guy, you gotta buddy, you gotta knock this
down, it's a danger, but don't build it up yet until after
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, nobody's going to listen to you. And even
if you tell them don't build it up unless you, you know,
the normal way yet. So if you want them to knock it
down, you gotta let them build it up. But רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, that would be if you need a special justification to build
it up. But of course רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say you
don't need a special justification, if it's a yard and it's there
that we gave you full allowance, opposed to if it's a field.
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, מתניתין
נמי דייקא, matnitin nami diyka, this also can be inferred from the
language of our
משנה. Mishnah. דקתני, Dekatani, our משנה Mishnah says, ובשביעית בונה כדרכו. ubashevi'it
boneh kedarko. By שביעית Shevi'it you can build the wall the normal
way. So what are we talking about? The wall of a garden
or the wall of your
yard? דהיכא, Deheicha, where is this wall? אילימא דחצר, Ileima dechatzer, if
it's a wall of your yard, צריכא למימרא? tsricha leimeira? Why do
you have to talk about, oh, it's allowed to build a wall
in your front yard on שמיטה. Shemitah. Maybe you should tell me
I can drive my car on שמיטה, Shemitah, I can do my
taxes on שמיטה. Shemitah. Meaning a wall in my front yard what?
Right. A wall in your front yard has absolutely nothing to do
with the issues of שמיטה. Shemitah. It's my yard, I'm not growing
anything there. So the fact that the משנה Mishnah needs to allow
it. שביעית Shviis would only make sense if it was in some
agricultural context, if it was a wall around my garden. So you
see that our משנה Mishnah is טאקע taka talking about garden walls;
our משנה Mishnah isn't addressing walls of yards. Okay? Now, so then
what is the חידוש chiddush even by a wall of a garden?
You're not working the land. So אלא
לאו דגינה, ella lav d'gina, it's talking about the wall of your
garden. ואף על גב דמחזי כמאן דעביד נטירותא לפירא, v'af al gav
d'mechezi k'man d'avid netiruta l'peira, and even though it looks like you're
doing it to protect the fruit, which is funny because you are
doing it to protect the fruit, but maybe the point is is
that as I've told you before, there's an issue about like protecting
the fruit as the way of demonstrating ownership. This is mine, everybody
else hands off. And there's a way of protecting the fruit which
is a problem on שמיטה; Shmitta; it's not just working the land.
There's an idea of sort of that sense of demonstrating the fact
of ownership. But there's another way of like protecting the fruits because
I don't want people trampling it, I certainly don't want animals trampling
it, and I don't want people just walking through as a shortcut.
Other ways of doing it for the sake of the fruit. So
therefore, and there so even though it looks like that's the problem,
which is funny because in a way that is what you're doing,
you are doing it נטירותא לפירא, netiruta l'peira, but I would think
that that is problematic. שמע מינה shma mina that it's not that
you're not working the land, number one, and number two, it's sort
of like the laying of the traps. You can do things that
protect the fruit, like laying of the traps protect the fruits if
you're not actually working the land and therefore it's okay. But I
did want to be clear that that's not... that there are ways
in which you can do things that are about demonstrating I own
this, which actually would be more problematic. So what we see is
the משנה Mishnah is talking about an agricultural context, a garden, and
therefore we have limitations. Therefore we have to say that it's allowed
on שמיטה; Shmitta; you might have thought not, it's blanket allowed on
שמיטה. Shmitta. And there's a little bit of a reservation in terms
of the חול המועד Chol HaMoed issue about doing it in a
slightly different way. But if it's your yard, then even on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed we allow you to build it up fully. Now
why? Again, the רשב"ם Rashbam said it's because your yard, it's about
protecting yourself from robbers. I mentioned the possible issue of a what
do you call it? Of privacy. Take a look at תוספות; Tosafot;
he sort of deals with this. תוספות Tosafot says אמר רב אשי
מתניתין נמי דייקא. amar Rav Ashi matnitin nami diyka.
פסקן pasken the תוספות Tosafot that Rav רבינו פרץ, Rabbeinu Peretz, so
that's an interesting one, תוספות Tosafot referring to another תוספות. Tosafot. דהלכתא
הכי, de'hilchata hachi,
that we rule this way, that you... in your yard you can
build it up normally. דכותל חצר מותר לבנותו. de'kotel chatzer mutar livnoto.
ופירש, u'peireish, but now here's what רבינו פרץ Rabbeinu Peretz says: היינו
דוקא במקום סמוך לרשות הרבים שיש לחוש לגנבי, haynu davka b'makom samuch
l'reshut harabim sheyesh lachush l'ganavei, אבל בין חצר לחצר משום בני חצר
אסור לבנות כדרכו. aval bein chatzer l'chatzer mishum bnei chatzer assur livnot
k'darko.
So if it's in your yard, if it's in like a courtyard,
right, and you're not and you're not exposed to random people in
the street, you're only exposed to your like next-door neighbor, so first
of all it's nice to live in a community where you don't
have to be worried about your next-door neighbor might be a גנב.
ganav. Okay, but clearly though there could be privacy concerns. So this
רבינו פרץ Rabbeinu Peretz specifically points out we're only giving you an
allowance because of a concern of robbers and not a concern of
privacy, which is quite fascinating given that the גמרא Gemara is
very sensitive to issues of privacy. So it's worth noting that at
least that's the way he interpreted it, but you could have said
otherwise. Okay, there was a question or two? Yes.
So the problem of the נטירה netira would be if you had
the perception you gave the perception that it was for commercial interest
that you were protecting the fruit because you wanted to do business
on שביעית? Shviis?
No, not only saying business, שביעית Shviis you're supposed to let the
fruit be הפקר hefker for everyone to come and get it, right?
So if you put barbed wire around your yard and said absolute
private property, no admittance, right, on שמיטה, Shmitta, even if you would
not have worked the land, that is a problem of letting the
fruit be free for all. So there's an issue about demonstrating protected
ownership. Not necessarily even that you want to sell it. Let's say
I'm just going to take it all for myself, right?
So yes, the distinction therefore is despite the fact that building a
wall might inhibit someone from coming and freely taking that fruit. Right.
I don't want you trampling on my...
Exactly, which is okay, right, yes. Exactly. Right. And that does raise
interesting questions, right, how do you sort of limit
the access to it in order to do what you gotta do
as a farmer and in order so it's not like people are
randomly coming in the whole time or whatever, and at the same
time not do it in a way that basically is saying, you
know, this is mine you can't touch. So that's an interesting issue
around שמיטה. Shmitta.
You leave the gate open. You leave the gate open, that's one
way to do it. We can have a sign that says please
ring for admittance or so I don't know, okay something like that.
Exactly, or exactly. All right, let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. Okay now we move from things that are like I
don't know yard-related, although we have been transitioning a little from actually
working the ground to traps and walls. Anyway, now we move to
a much more broader issues around חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Let's take
a look. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir says, רואה.
ro'eh. רואין את הנגעים, Ro'in et hanega'im, some have the גרסה girsa
בתחילה, betchila, some don't. רואין את הנגעים להקל ולא להחמיר. Ro'in et
hanega'im lehakel velo lehachmir. If somebody has a spot on their body
and they think it might be צרעת tzara'at or it's already been
identified before חול המועד Chol HaMoed as possible צרעת tzara'at and they've
been put in
quarantine, הסגר, hesger, then the question is can you inspect it or
reinspect it? That question of בתחילה betchila might be relevant to that.
Can you inspect that spot on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? What? To
reinspect, don't you have to? Well, we'll take a look, we'll take
a look. Okay. You don't have to do it exactly a week
later. It's a minimum of a week later. Yeah. Okay, so he
says you can look at it and if it's okay then you
can say oh you're טהור. tahor. But if it's not okay you
could say you know what, let's talk after חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
Okay, so that's why I had a there's somebody who does you
know
procedures. You know when you're like at the hospital they have like
not the radiologist, they have someone else who sort of does the
X-rays or whatever or the ultrasound and they're not allowed to tell
you what they're actually seeing. They say the doctor will speak to
you. So once in a while I had somebody who said to
me like, like, I can tell you if it's okay. They're sort
of like, so great! So if you'll tell me I can't tell
you what this is! Then it's like ah! What's happening? Oh my
god! What's the doctor going to say? Anyway, it's the same type
of thing. You can say okay, you can say when it's okay.
You can't say when it's not okay. What? Would you call that
guy מרת נפש?
marat nefesh? Because then he knows well, we'll talk about that.
So that's what we're going to talk about. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you can look at it to be lenient but if
it's but if you're going to have to say טמא, tamei, then
you don't respond. I'll tell you we'll talk after חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed.
וחכמים אומרים VeChachamim omrim and the sages say לא להקל ולא להחמיר.
lo lehakel velo lehachmir. Don't look at it at all on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay. Now why not? You might say exactly for
the reason I said that if you say we can't talk about
it now then you're effectively telling the guy טמא tamei even if
it doesn't halachically change his status it's still like you know bad
news. But let's take a look at what the that's not what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
So the second time all
right, so the גמרא Gemara will address all of this. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes, yesterday I thought you mentioned that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was
considered the חכמים. Chachamim. Is that in that?
Yeah, so that's a very good point. You're right. I said I
said often. You're absolutely correct. Here you have רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
as the first and חכמים Chachamim as the alternative voice. Right. So
very often רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is חכמים, Chachamim, especially if he's
not already mentioned and often if it's like in response to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but it's certainly no not a rule by any
means. Okay. תניא Tanya we taught in a ברייתא brayta רבי מאיר
אומר רואין את הנגעים להקל ולא להחמיר. Rabbi Meir omer ro'in et
hanega'im lehakel velo lehachmir.
You could see these spots in order to be lenient but not
in order to be strict. You wouldn't rule on it if it's
bad. רבי יוסי אומר לא להקל ולא להחמיר. Rabbi Yossi omer lo
lehakel velo lehachmir. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says no, don't look at
it at all. So that now we see that he's the חכמים.
Chachamim. שאם אתה נזקק לו להקל נזקק לו אף להחמיר. She'im ata
nizkak lo lehakel nizkak lo af lehachmir.
So here the reason is not because oh my god you're going
to get him upset because he'll know be able to be figured
it out. But no. He basically says once you have to once
you're addressing the case, you've got to give him an answer. So
you know you could say I'm not going to look at it
today, come back to the office after חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But
if you're looking at it, if you're נזקק לו, nizkak lo, you're
sort of you're obligated to him to look at it and to
respond, then you have to respond one way or the other. אמר
רבי נראין דברי רבי מאיר במוסגר ודברי רבי יוסי
במוחלט. Amar Rabbi nirin divrei Rabbi Meir bemusgar vedivrei Rabbi Yossi bemuchlat.
So here's going to get a little confusing but he says we
rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in a guy that's מוסגר musgar
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in a guy that's מוחלט. muchlat. Now
what's the difference between מוסגר musgar and מוחלט? muchlat?
So and also what does he mean by נראין? nirin? But first
of all we'll take a look. Okay. So here you've got a
guy
there's my guy he's
got a נגע nega and he's got a spot.
Okay here. He's got a spot on him. Okay anyway. Okay so
he shows it to a כהן. Kohen. So the כהן Kohen can
do one of two things. He could either say טהור. tahor. Actually
what we can do is we could okay, so he could say
he could say טהור tahor and then he goes and then he's
in the safe zone. Or he could say he could say טמא.
tamei.
What? Well no the first we get is the first week. So
this is the first appearance. The first and the thing he could
say is or he could say let's give it a week. That's
your choice there. How do you draw those decision things? Like that
right?
Isn't that how those flow charts? Okay טהור tahor and he says
wait. Okay. So now he's in this waiting period okay which is
called מוסגר. musgar. הסגירו הכהן. Hisgiro haKohen. Okay quarantine. He's locked up
till we look at it again. Okay he's a מוסגר. musgar. Okay.
Then comes the second time that he appears before the כהן. Kohen.
Now there's three possibilities here.
Without the נגע? nega? Well about exactly.
Three possibilities and I'm not going to go into all of them.
One הלכה halacha is that it basically went away so you're טהור.
tahor. Okay. One possibility is it's gone. One possibility is that it's
gotten bigger okay it grew and
then you are and then you are completely טמא. tamei. Okay and
this is called מוחלט. muchlat. Okay so talk about it in a
minute.
And then the third possibility is it stayed the same. Stayed. Okay
and then you appear the third time before the כהן Kohen and
then based on what happened. Either you are going to be מוחלט
muchlat or טהור. tahor. Okay? So anyway, so at time two or
time after one week this is week I mean it might be
a little confusing this is week one
this is week two. Okay? So here you're מוסגר, musgar, you might
do a leapfrog and become a מוחלט muchlat if it grew from
week one to week two, but here you're basically a מוסגר. musgar.
If it grew
and or other things but anyway you can become a מוחלט. muchlat.
What is the difference? Okay the basic difference is the גמרא Gemara
in מגילה Megillah says אין בין מצורע מוסגר למצורע מוחלט אלא פריעה
ופרימה, ein bein Metzora Musgar leMetzora Muchlat ela Pria U'frima,
the tearing of the garments, the growing the hair wild. But basically,
interestingly, the basic status during these periods, whether you're here is when
you have the hair and the
and the garments, but the basic status during all these periods is
pretty much the same, which is you're fully
טמא. tamei. Okay? And
and what we're going to see is an interesting question about whether
you're if it's a man is he allowed to be with his
wife. Okay, but he's fully טמא, tamei, he's חייב chayav in קרבנות
korbanot etcetera etcetera. Okay, anyway, so but whoops actually not that part
whatever hold up I forget the חייב קרבנות chayav korbanot part.
Okay
anyway, so that's the status. Okay, now when are you appearing before
the כהן? kohein? So what becomes here? I mean what right
whatever. So so let's take a look at what he says. אמר
רבא בטהור Amar Rava be'tahor okay I'm sorry let's do that again.
אמר רבי ניכרין דברי רבי מאיר במוסגר ודברי רבי יוסי במוחלט. Amar
Rabbi Nichrin divrei Rabbi Meir be'musgar ve'divrei Rabbi Yose be'muchlat. Now
when he says ניכרין דברי רבי מאיר Nichrin divrei Rabbi Meir it's
confusing because if you ever really פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, right, so to פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir means
that you're saying that you can look at it and just be
and just say and just say nothing. So if you're willing to
פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you might as well פסקן
pasken him in all the cases, just look at it and just
say nothing, that's the problem. So it's actually quite confusing, the language
and תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion why there's such a big
תוספות Tosafot here. But really what it means is think about רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, not that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says say nothing if it's a problem, but think about
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says you look at it and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says you don't look at it. So meaning רבי Rebbi is basically
assuming like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. If you're going to look at
it, you're going to have to give him the answer one way
or the other. He's assuming like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, you can't
just give him one answer without the you can't just choose which
answer I'm only going to give you one type of an answer.
If you're going to look at it you got to give him
the answer. So when it says ניכרין דברי רבי מאיר Nichrin divrei
Rabbi Meir it means we're going to look at it in this
case and we're not going to look at it in the other
case. But if we're going to look at it, we're not really
going to go like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if we're going to
look at it we're going to tell you one way or the
other. Okay? So here's what he says. ניכרין דברי רבי מאיר במוסגר
ודברי רבי יוסי במוחלט. Nichrin divrei Rabbi Meir be'musgar ve'divrei Rabbi Yose
be'muchlat. So if you're in this category you'll be prepared to look
at it. Okay? Whereas if you're in this category מוחלט muchlat you're
not going to be prepared to look at it. Now why? You
would say if you're in the מוחלט muchlat it's like the better
situation, can't get any worse, can only get any better, can only
get better. If you're in this category maybe it'll get better but
maybe it'll get worse. So if anything if you want to get
one of the times to look at it it should be מוחלט
muchlat not
מוסגר. musgar. Alright? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about
this. The גמרא's Gemara going to circle back to that. אמר רבא
Amar Rava בטהור be'tahor if the guy is totally טהור, tahor, he's
just seen it he has yet to appear before כהן, kohein, כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דלא חזי ליה. kulei alma lo pligi delo chazi
leh.
Everybody agrees meaning don't look at him. Meaning not everybody you know
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir again we're not dealing yeah yeah before we're
not dealing with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. We're basically dealing again with
the assumption if you're going to look at it you're going to
give a ruling either way. But if the guy is totally טהור
tahor everybody would agree don't look at him because if you look
at it you might have to give a ruling and make a
טהור tahor person into טמא. tamei. So again bracketing רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, assuming you're going to give the ruling one way or the
other, if it's a טהור tahor guy don't look at him. Okay,
בהסגר ראשון כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחזי ליה. be'hasger rishon kulei alma
lo pligi dechazi leh. If you're in status one everybody would agree
that you would look at it. Why? בהסגר I'm sorry בהסגר ראשון
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחזי ליה, you would look at it. Why?
Because what is possible to happen to me if I'm in this
status and you look at it? I'm already טמא tamei so I'm
already טמא tamei so either I'm going to get better and you're
going to look at it here and tell me I'm טהור tahor
or you're going to tell me wait another week. Well I'm already
in that status so it's not much of
a difference so you might as well look at it here and
maybe get me off free and the worst case scenario is it'll
just continue into week two. So everybody agrees that you do look
at it in that case. I understand. Okay now the גמרא Gemara
continues כי פליגי ki pligi
what do we debate? And there's a big תוספות Tosafot also that
re-reads it in different ways which I'm not going to talk about.
it's confusing enough as it is. כי פליגי, Ki paligi, what do
they debate? בהסגר שני, Be-hesger sheni,
the second status. מר סבר בכהן תליא מילתא. Mar savar be-kohen talya
milta. אי טהור אמר ליה טהור ואי טמא שתיק. Ei tahor amar
lei tahor ve-ei tamei shatik. So if it's this case, right, so
here what he's saying is, now I'm sorry we are back to
Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yose. Everybody would agree in this case like
why even bother looking at him? Okay, he's טהור tahor already. You
don't have to make him טהור. tahor. Best thing you could do
is do nothing. Everybody would agree in this case that even Rabbi
Yose, you might as well look at him and give him the
ruling because even though Rabbi Yose feels you have to give him
either ruling, but okay, the טהור tahor ruling would be great, the
טמא tamei ruling won't be so bad. So even Rabbi Yose would
say why not look at him here. Okay, here the question is
would we look at him at this case? Because at this case
you could really make him worse or you could really make him
better. So therefore Rabbi Meir will say look at him and only
give him when it's a good ruling. And Rabbi Yose will say
I don't want to look at him because if I look at
him I might have to give him the bad ruling and I'm
going to make him even worse. How can he make him worse?
Because you're making him from מוסגר musgar to מוחלט muchlat which is
a more complete status. I mean it certainly got that whole thing
about טמא טמא יקרא, tamei tamei yikra, even though it's the same
in terms of טומאה, tumah, socially it's a big difference. Okay.
So that position treats the third case like the first case. You
can only make it worse, right? For טהור tahor don't look at
him at all.
Well no, here it's not you can only make it worse, you
could make it better. You could say טהור. tahor. But there's a
chance you'll make him worse.
Okay. Like in the first case. Why not look at him at
all? You can only make it worse right?
So you don't. So Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yose agree don't bother
looking at this guy. Okay, meaning because
everybody would say why bother looking? You only make it worse. Here
Rabbi Meir would say of course you look at him because I'll
give you a good answer, I won't give you a bad answer.
Even Rabbi Meir would look at him because even a bad answer
won't be so bad and there's a possibility that it'll be the
best answer. Right. Here though is where they really debate. Right? Because
here Rabbi Meir will always say look at him, you can only
make it better. Okay, but Rabbi Yose will say no, here you
could really make it worse and I don't want to look at
him.
By week number two couldn't it have spread?
Yeah so תוספות Tosafot asks that question. So תוספות Tosafot says wait
one minute here, if it spread you're going to go into this
category. Right, so I was a little bit afraid to give you
that piece of information because that's תוספות's Tosafot's question which leads תוספות
Tosafot to lead to a totally different read of the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay not totally different, but can we bracket it? If we're done
with the גמרא Gemara as we have it we can get back
and address that. תוספות Tosafot asks that question. Okay. Yeah.
Is it possible that a person who is in this state is
in a state of increased concern?
Oh that's such an excellent point.
Right, so
you may be able to relieve him of that concern whereas in
this case you don't want to make him more concerned, he's already
concerned. Right.
So that's an excellent point. So there's a תוספות Tosafot that actually
makes that issue. I'll just read you the one line where let
me just see if I can find it
where he actually talks about טרחא tircha
right here, it says טרחא דגברא. tircha de-gavra. Right. Here, four lines
down in the תוספות Tosafot on the wide lines on ז' עמוד
א' Zayin amud aleph he
says: וגם יש שיצטער שעד עתה היה מצפה לטהור ואין מצפה עתה
להטהר. Ve-gam yesh she-yitzta'er she-ad ata haya mitzape le-tahor ve-ein mitzape ata
le-hitaher. So he deals with like certain cases about he says look,
in this case there's part of his critique of this read of
the גמרא Gemara we just did. In this case you figure oh
it's only one week, it'll probably be fine, I'll probably be able.
Then if you rule
טמא, tamei, you're not only perpetuating his status but you're making him
feel that he's stuck in his status, right? He's not like about
to turn over. And you're saying a different concern which is the
anxiety of not knowing one way or the other. Right, so those
תוספות Tosafot actually does touch on those issues. I mean those are
very legitimate points, although it's not explicitly addressed in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so let's take a look. So בהסגר שני, Be-hesger sheni, מר
סבר בכהן תליא מילתא. Mar savar be-kohen talya milta. So Rabbi Meir
said I'm willing to look at him even in the second stage.
He says look, בכהן תליא מילתא, be-kohen talya milta, the כהן kohen
completely has discretion whether to give the ruling or not. אי טהור
אמר ליה טהור ואי טמא שתיק. Ei tahor amar lei tahor ve-ei
tamei shatik. If he's טהור tahor say טהור tahor and if he's
טמא tamei says we'll talk about it later, you don't give an
answer. And therefore you can look at him even in the case
where it could be really bad because you just don't give the
ruling. And without giving the ruling the status does not obtain, right?
He does not become טמא tamei until the כהן kohen utters the
ruling. And that's an important thing to realize about all of this.
The כהן kohen is not just discovering a reality which is always
there. The הלכה halakha status only results from the utterance of the
כהן. kohen. And therefore by not giving the ruling the guy does
not become worse off because you know at that stage. ומר סבר,
U-mar savar, but Rabbi Yose holds לטהרו או לטמאו כתיב. le-taharo o
le-tame'o ketiv. Yes it's true the uttering of the כהן kohen determines
his status, but you cannot choose once you're looking at him whether
you're going to give him an answer or not give him an
answer. It says he appears before the כהן kohen then the כהן
kohen will be
מטהר metaher him or
מטמא. metamei. Okay so that's where we are. אמר מר אמר רבי
Rabbi, *Amar Mar Amar Rebbe* so that's the issue about they fundamentally
here everybody agrees why not look at him you won't make it
really worse everybody agrees why look at him there's no way you
can make it better and the debate is this guy. Okay now
we get to this issue about נראין דברי רבי Rabbi מאיר *nirin
divrei Rebbe Meir* if there's a way for Rebbe to say like
some split the vote. So not really splitting the vote because again
Rebbe is assuming that if you're going to look at him you're
going to have to rule one way or the other but sometimes
we'll look at him sometimes we won't. אמר רבי Rebbi נראין דברי
רבי Rebbi יוסי במחלט ודברי רבי Rebbi מאיר במוסגר *Amar Rebbe nirin
divrei Rebbe Yossi b'muchlat u'divrei Rebbe Meir b'musgar*. Okay we will rule
that you won't look at him במחלט *b'muchlat* in this guy now
we're talking about this guy here because it's already in the worst
status. Okay you won't look at it here but you will be
willing to look at it in one of these statuses now that
is completely counterintuitive if anybody you're going to look at it's the
guy that's already in the worst state can't get any worse right?
But that's his first version. Okay let's take a look. נראין דברי
רבי Rebbi יוסי *nirin divrei Rebbe Yossi* we won't look at him
במחלט *b'muchlat* the guy that's in the full state ודברי רבי Rebbi
מאיר במוסגר *u'divrei Rebbe Meir b'musgar* but we will look at him
like Rebbe Meir we'll have to give him one way or the
other an answer but we'll look at him in the guy that's
in the middle state which is counterintuitive. והתניא Vehatanya, איפכא *ve'hatanya ipcha*
we have a ברייתא braita: *braita* that says the opposite the opposite
of what makes sense. Here we'll look at him it might get
worse but it might get better. I'm sorry here we won't look
at him because here there's a good chance that he'll get worse
right? Here of course we're going to look at him he can
only get better. Okay that completely makes sense. Alright what should be
the logic to say the opposite? So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says תנאי היא אליבא דרבי *tannai hi aliba
d'Rebbe*. There's a debate about which was Rebbe's way of splitting the
vote. מר סבר savar, צוותא דעלמא עדיף ליה ומר סבר Umar savar,
צוותא דאשתו עדיף ליה *mar savar tzavta d'alma adif lei u'mar savar
tzavta d'ishto adif lei*. The question is would you rather have the
company of your friends or the company of your wife? You don't
need to answer that. Okay so now what does that mean? It
means that okay it means that again of course we're assuming a
male מצורע metzora *metzora* but a male מצורע metzora, *metzora* is the
one that the תורה Torah *Torah* says it says וישב מחוץ לאהלו
שבעת ימים ve-yashav michutz le-ohalo shivat yamim, *v'yashav michutz l'ohalo shivat yamim*.
Now do people know where it says by the מצורע metzora. *metzora*
וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים shivat yamim, *v'yashav michutz l'ohalo shivat yamim*?
Once he has been looked at here and said you're טהור tahor
*tahor* you got a good check of health then we're going to
go through a seven-day process of טהרה tahara. *taharah* seven-day טהרה tahara
*taharah* right and then in the end you're going to have the
whole birds and the whole thing that comes out whatever right that's
the beginning of פרשת מצורע Parshat Metzora, *parshat Metzora* and during that
seven-day process of טהרה tahara *taharah* it says וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת
ימים *v'yashav michutz l'ohalo shivat yamim*.
So the question is here it's assumed to be that he can't
have sex with his wife okay but because he has been told
that he is טהור tahor *tahor* okay he can actually or he's
in the process of טהרה tahara. *taharah* whatever he can actually go
back to the camp. Okay so in this period
no wife or not having sex with his wife you know yes
he's back in the camp. Okay in this period okay and by
the way
well in this period okay the answer is or let's say when
he's here you're assuming that here since it's not yet you can't
say this verse even though here he's מחוץ למחנה *michutz l'machaneh* his
wife can come with
him outside the camp right?
No camp okay but yes wife.
Okay so then now the question is will you look at this
guy on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*? So you could say it can
only get better. Yeah it could get better but you know in
the process of getting better it gets worse in that he has
to separate from his wife. So maybe it's so ironic though to
think about that that somebody wouldn't want to get better even though
even if it's true he'd rather be with his wife than be
in the camp. Who doesn't want to be getting better? You know
so anyway but the idea that you don't look at this guy
is because he'd rather not start getting better he'd rather be with
his wife even if he has to be out of the camp
and if you're going to tell him טהור tahor *tahor* he's going
to have to start getting better he's going to have to be
without his wife even though he goes back in the camp. So
therefore you don't look at him as opposed to this guy you
do look at. Why do you look at this guy? Because again
if it gets better you get you know if it's this stage
he gets better he gets totally better right? He doesn't have to
go through this process. If it's this stage he gets better he
gets totally better and if he gets worse or stays the same
it's just all the same because in this entire period here okay
in this entire period he's מחוץ למחנה *michutz l'machaneh* מוסגר musgar. *musgar*.
The only difference with this guy is the hair and the garments
or whatever the entire period.
Isn't that what we said was a worse way?
It is worse yes the so now the The question, so I'll
tell you what I mean. In this entire period he's חוץ למחנה.
chutz lamachaneh Okay? So you look at him here because the חוץ
למחנה chutz lamachaneh thing is not going to change, right? He's going
to stay חוץ למחנה chutz lamachaneh. and the wife thing is going
to stay with it. So you might as well look at him
here. Ah, but if he's here, don't look at him because then
he'll start getting better and he won't be able to be with
his wife. That's that logic. The other logic is the much more
logical one, which is people want to be better. So therefore, in
this case you will look at him because he'll be in the
process of getting better, and in this case you won't look at
him because he can get worse. Now the question is, what do
you mean get worse? We've been saying get worse is that he
gets socially ostracized, but you're telling me that in all these cases
he's חוץ למחנה. chutz lamachaneh So the thing is, yes, but he's
more ostracized here. Here is where the hair goes wild, the garments
are rent, טמא טמא יקרא. tamei tamei yikra.
So even though he's not just living outside the city, he's really
in a state of ostracization. Okay, so that is the two ways
of looking at it. Yeah.
But Jonathan, what you just said is reflected by way of understanding
the similarity between the מצורע metzora and אבילות. aveilut. As they say,
before it becomes an אבל aveil during the מועד moed they stay
together with their family, etc., right? And the אבילות aveilut doesn't kick
in until after the מועד moed even though they're suffering personal-national, right?
That is an excellent point and that is a theme that we're
going to see repeated a lot and thank you for bringing that
up about אבילות aveilut and מצורע, metzora, similar practices and similar issues.
Excellent. Okay, so let's continue back in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, למימרא
Lemeimra says the גמרא Gemara דמוחלט demuchlat מותר בתשמיש המטה? mutar betashmish
hamitah?
What,
you're telling me when you're in that worst state, you're still allowed
to be with your wife? והתניא, we learn a ברייתא: Beraita, וישב
מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים, שאסור בתשמיש המטה, she-asur betashmish hamitah,
forbidden in sex, but that's during the period of טהרה. tahara ואין
אהלו אלא אשתו, Ve-ein ohalo ela ishto, and your tent means your
wife, שנאמר, shenemar, again assuming the male here, לך אמור להם שובו
לכם לאהליכם. lech emor lahem shuvu lachem le-oholeichem. So ואתה פה עמוד
עמדי, ve-ata po amod imadi, says from where we learned that משה
Moshe was אסור בתשמיש המטה. asur betashmish hamitah. Exactly
how we know it's wife is in the context of the fact
that before מתן תורה Mattan Torah they had to separate from their
wives. שובו לכם לאהליכם shuvu lachem le-oholeichem is understood in that context.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer שבעת ימים, so it says for
seven days, ומחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים umichutz le-ohalo shivat yamim יספרו לו,
yisperu lo, for those seven days he counts, ימי ספורו ולא ימי
חלוטו. yemei sipuro velo yemei chaluto. During the period of counting, the
טהרה period is when he's forbidden in his wife, but not during
the period of being חלוט, chalut, of being totally ostracized and being
cut off. That's a period where even though he's חוץ למחנה and
he's in the worst state, he's still מותר mutar to his wife.
The problem with sex with his wife only begins during the טהרה
period. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda omer זין
ימי ספורו קל וחומר מימי חלוטו, zayin yemei sipuro kal vachomer mi-yemei
chaluto, which is the logical thing to say. He says are you
kidding me? He says if in the process of becoming טהור the
תורה Torah is saying you can't be with your wife, certainly when
you're טמא tamei you can't be with your wife, right? If even
though you're being טהור you can't be with your wife. So that's
what he says.
And then the whole time?
So he says right, and certainly starting with חלוטו. chaluto. I don't
know if he would say it from מוסגר. I don't know, but
he certainly said you know that here it's already אסור asur with
the wife. So according to him you would certainly look at the
guy at this stage because it could only get better. Okay, ואמר
רבי חייא, ve-amar Rabbi Chiyya, says רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, דנתי לפני
רבי, danti lifnei Rabbi,
I discussed this in front of
רבי, Rebbi למדתנו רבנו, limadtanu rabbenu, our master you've taught us, יותם
לא היה לו לעוזיהו אלא בימי חלוטו. Yotam lo haya lo le-Uziyahu
ela bi-yemei chaluto. So that יותם Yotam was only born to עוזיהו
Uziyahu and תוספות Tosafot figures out how they get this from the
פסוקים pesukim during the period when he was חלוט chalut because עוזיהו
Uziyahu was a מצורע. metzora
So and therefore somehow the גמרא Gemara had a tradition or figured
out based on the verses that his wife, that עוזיהו Uziyahu although
he was a מצורע metzora and he was a מוחלט, muchlat, a
full
מצורע, metzora his wife conceived his son during that period. So he
was having sex during that period. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said
back to him, אף אני כך אמרתי. Af ani kach amarti. So
yeah, I agree, I say that. Meaning, yeah, I agree you can
have sex during the period of חלוטה chaluta only not during the
period of
טהרה. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? What’s the debate?
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b’Rabbi Yehuda סבר, גלי רחמנא בימי
ספורו וכל שכן בימי חלוטו. gali Rachmana bimei sefuro vechol shekein bimei
chaluto. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b’Rabbi Yehuda says look, the
Torah tells you no sex during the period of the counting and
the טהרה period, so of course if during the period of becoming
טהור no, it’s a קל וחמר kal vachomer the period when you’re
most
טמא. tamei. ומר סבר, no, מאי דגלי גלי ומאי דלא גלי לא
גלי. mai degali gali u’mai dela gali la gali. What it tells
me it tells me, what it doesn’t tell me it doesn’t tell
me. Okay, I’m taking a minimalist read. All of these things are
you know are somewhat you know not logical, they’re just whatever the
Torah says, so I’ll only apply this in that period.
Now you could say that about any קל וחמר. kal vachomer.
Right, exactly, and תוספות Tosafot sort of asks that. Okay, so excellent
point Rabbi Dov, so if you look at the little תוספות Tosafot
מאי דלא גלי לא גלי, mai dela gali la gali, תוספות Tosafot
says יש מקשים, yeish makshim, למה אין רבי דורש קל וחמר? lama
ein Rabbi doreish kal vachomer? האי אדם דן קל וחמר מאצמו. hai
adam dan kal vachomer me’atzmo. What do you mean you can’t just
say I reject the קל וחמר kal vachomer because I just go
by the פסוק? pasuk? ושמא יש שום טרחא v’shema yeish shum tircha
או שמא מצורע חידוש הוא. o shema metzora chidush hu. Either he
has some logical challenge or maybe he feels and that’s what the
line I was throwing out, which is the whole idea of מצורע
is not logical, meaning it’s not illogical but it’s like arbitrary. And
if you assume all the rules are relatively arbitrary then you can’t
use logic in a system that’s arbitrary. Okay, okay, and then he
goes on and maybe he has a hint from the verse, etc.
but that’s an excellent point.
Okay, למימרא, L’meimra, now the גמרא Gemara gets back to the other
point, למימרא דבכהן תליא מילתא? l’meimra d’vekohein talya milta? Are you telling
me that it all depends on the כהן? kohein? Meaning that if
the כהן kohein doesn’t utter the words, he’s not טמא, tamei, which
is clearly the assumption we’ve been working with according to everyone? אין,
In, yes, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, וביום הראות בו,
uv’yom hera’ot bo, on the day he you know he sees the
the spot is you know is shown to him.
ובשרו חי, U’vesaro chai, is that one?
Yes. But basically the פסוק pasuk says what do you mean on
the day that the spot is is presented is you know is
appears to him? So the גמרא Gemara says יש יום
שאתה רואה yeish yom she’atah ro’eh ויש יום שאי אתה רואה בו.
v’yeish yom she’ei atah ro’eh bo. There are days that you agree
to look at the spot, ביום b’yom only on the day that
it’s chosen to be shown and there are days that you don’t
agree to look at the spot. So
hold on I just want to see one thing. Okay,
so on the days you don’t look at the spot, מכאן אמרו,
mikan amru, from here they said חתן שנולד בו נגע, chatan shenolad
bo nega, if a groom has a spot נותנים לו שבעת ימי
המשתה, notnim lo shivat yemei hamishte, you give him the seven days
of rejoicing of the partying, לו ולביתו ולכסותו, lo u’leveito u’liksuto,
not just the spot on his body but even if it’s a
spot on his garments or on his house, which is big deal.
So there’s תנא, Tanna, so it doesn’t affect him, he’s still okay.
No, somehow that would be considered to be a set of like
anguish and you don’t look at him, you don’t bother him with
these things for the whole week. וכן ברגל, V’chein baregel, and similarly
on a רגל, regel, נותנים לו שבעת ימי הרגל, notnim lo shivat
yemei haregel, you don’t if somebody has a spot you don’t deal
with it for the whole רגל, regel, you don’t look at it,
דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that’s what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, now okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
here says you don’t look at it and it’s interesting because according
to him it’s not just you don’t look at it because you
don’t want to like make it worse, you don’t look at it
because you don’t want to have the guy deal with it for
the entire during that period during that period. Okay, and so that’s
the position that there are days that you can choose not to
see and that presumably if we’re choosing not to see, it doesn’t
mean he’s טמא tamei but he doesn’t know about it, it’s also
the idea that the כהן’s kohein utterance will determine whether or not
he’s טמא. tamei. So בכהן תליא מילתא vekohein talya milta might mean
that you know the כהן kohein gets to choose or whatever the
כהן kohein has the right under certain circumstances not to look at
it, but also by not looking at it the guy’s status has
not yet changed. Okay, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, אינו צריך, eino tzarich,
you don’t learn it need to learn it out from the verse
וביום הראות בו. uv’yom hera’ot bo. I can get give you this
idea from another verse that you can use your discretion whether or
not to look at something.
He always agrees with the position but not with the derivation.
Exactly, הרי הוא אומר, Harei hu omer, the verse says וצוה הכהן
ופנו את הבית, v’tzivah hakohein u’pinu et habayit, that when somebody says
has a spot on the house he calls the כהן kohein and
the כהן kohein clears out the house, this is explicit in the
verse so that there’s nothing in the house when the כהן kohein
declares it
טמא, tamei, ולא יטמא כל אשר בבית, v’lo yitma kol asher babayit,
the stuff inside of the house won’t become טמא. tamei. So therefore
what do you see? You see that you can wait, let’s say
it’s going to take a day to clear the stuff out. You
see you can wait in order to look at something in order
so that your ruling will not be an over an undue burden.
Okay, so רבי Rebbi says if you can do it there where
the only issue is just like a דבר הרשות, devar hareshut, it’s
not like I’m engaging in a מצוה mitzvah or something, it’s just
you know it’s just like a you know it’s inconvenient and even
so we allow ourselves to wait. Certainly you can allow yourself to
wait in cases where the guy’s really engaged in a מצוה, mitzvah,
שמחת הרגל, simchat haregel, שמחת הנישואין, simchat hanisuin, how much more so
can the כהן kohein choose to wait rather than to
see. Exactly, that
is an excellent proof from the verse that the טומאה tumah is
created by the utterance of the כהן, kohen, because if the טומאה
tumah was already there, then how would it matter whether he uttered
it before or after? So excellent. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
אם ממתינים לו לדבר רשות, כל שכן לדבר מצוה. Im mamtinin lo
l'dvar rashut, kol shekein l'dvar mitzvah. If you wait for him for
a matter of discretion that he's involved in, meaning it's an inconvenience
but it's not like he's it's a מצוה mitzvah that it would
compromise, how much more so would you not, would you postpone looking
at it if it would compromise a מצוה? mitzvah? שמחת רגל, Simchas
of Regel, שמחת נישואין. Simchas of Nisuin.
By touching?
Yes, by touching.
מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What's the difference between them? Like okay, he
quoted a different פסוק, pasuk, who cares? So אמר אביי משמעות דורשין
איכא בינייהו. Amar Abaye mashmaut dorshin ika beinaihu. Yeah, the only difference
is about how you derive it, there's no difference in הלכה. halacha.
ורבא אמר דבר רשות איכא בינייהו. V'Rava amar d'var rashut ika beinaihu.
No,
there is a difference because רבי is learning it from a פסוק
pasuk about areas that are not מצוות, mitzvos, areas that are discretionary
areas. So let's say it's not the case about clearing out the
house and it's not the case that the guy's involved in רגל
regel or getting married, but the person just says, look, buddy כהן,
kohen, I'm in the middle of an important business deal here, I
got to you know whatever, can we do this a week from
now? Let me fit you into my schedule, okay? So would that
be allowed? Okay, so רבי would say, well why not? You learn
from the case of the house that you can use your discretion,
and if it's too big of an inconvenience you can wait for
a later time to see it. Whereas the other דרשה drasha learns
it from ביום הראות בו B'yom heraot bo and sees it like
your special days that you don't see, and limits it to cases
of like מצוה mitzvah of like רגל regel and married and does
not give the כהן kohen wide discretion in terms of when to
see it. Yeah.
Just as a matter of process, I don't know who summons the
כהן kohen to look at...
That's a good question. Right. So I've actually written about this, you
know, the language in the פסוקים psukim is very much והובא אל
הכהן, v'huva el hakohen, he's brought. And you know, if you look
at the whole language in פרשת מצורע, it's very much that the
מצורע is completely in the passive and he's being brought by other
people. Anyway, so I've written about that about you know how that's
like reflective of the reality of like the medical profession and illness
and that you're sort of made into an object and you know
you sort of you lose your autonomy
in those cases. But the תורה Torah does say he's brought, but
the rabbis understand so anyway, why like that? Why can't I just
decide never to go to the כהן? kohen?
By the owner or by the neighbors?
Well no, it might be the person himself, not just the house
or whatever, the person is brought. Yeah. So anyway, the rabbis do
more put in issues of autonomy and self-direction and also like seeing
the person as a subject and not as an object. One of
the ways actually that I make the point is exactly this point,
that we will acknowledge that you're involved in a wedding, you're involved
in the רגל regel or whatever, so we acknowledge your human reality,
you know, and we don't just completely... so we actually see you
as a person. But in terms of the issue of bringing of
coming to the כהן, kohen, yeah, they also learned that there's an
obligation to present yourself to the כהן. kohen. But in understanding that
there is that obligation, they've also made you more of an agent,
right? You're not just being controlled by others.
But even then, you do outdoors, so it's not like you're
going to the כהן's kohen apartment or his house. He has to
be... right? Because he has to make sure there's natural light and
other qualifications. Okay, so... all right, fine. So there's still like you
know you're not totally beholden to the
כהן kohen because he has to also go out to... Yeah, but
that doesn't define who's controlling it. Okay, so ורבא אמר דבר רשות
איכא בינייהו. V'Rava amar d'var rashut ika beinaihu. The question is choosing
to postpone it for a matter of discretion, not because of like
a מצוה mitzvah of the רגל regel or the נישואין. nisuin. Okay.
And therefore if רבי is learning it out from the פסוק pasuk
of cleaning the house, רבי would give the כהן kohen a wide
range of discretion as
to when to see it. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, the גמרא
Gemara... מהתם לא גמרינן. mehasam lo gamrinan. No, no, you can't learn
out from the postponing by the house to apply to cases of
postponing when it's on your body. Why? דחידוש הוא, de-chiddush hu,
the whole case of the house is a חידוש, chiddush, the whole
case of מצורע is a חידוש, chiddush, but the house in particular.
Why? דהא עצים ואבנים בעלמא לא מטמאו. deha eitzim va-avanim b'alma lo
mitamm'u.
I mean,
you're talking about the wood and the bricks of the house. Normally,
that type of raw material is not טמא. tamei. Things only if
they are vessels are טמא. tamei. Wood, a stone is טמא? tamei?
The whole case is completely doesn't fit any normal category. So if
the תורה wants to give some discretion there, fine. It doesn't mean
you have the same discretion when it's a טומאה tumah on the
body. Okay? והכא מטמא, v'hacha mitammei, here it's טמא, tamei, yeah.
In other words, the house itself is a vessel?
First of all, it's not
it's built on the ground and something that's מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka
isn't טמא. tamei. So and number two is even after you destroy
it, the stones retain their טומאה. tumah. You would never have something
like that in normal הלכה. halacha. Okay, so the גמרא... Gemara. so
the whole thing is... so yes, you have discretion by the house,
but the house is a חידוש. chiddush. You don't have the same
discretion when it's on the body. ורבי אמר, v'Rebbi amar,
רבי would say back to you, איצטריך, itztarich, I'm going to get...
I'm going to get it from, I got it from the פסוק
pasuk that you have the discretion by the house, and I still
use the פסוק pasuk of וביום הראות בו. uv'yom heraot bo. How
do you do that? דאיכתב רחמנא וביום הראות בו, de'ikasav Rachmana uv'yom
heraot bo, if you just had that verse you were starting with,
some days you see, some days you don't, tell you to exclude
cases of מצוה, mitzvah, הוי אמינא לדבר מצוה אין לדבר רשות לא,
havi amina l'dvar mitzvah in l'dvar reshus lo, I would have come
to your conclusion, that it's רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda conclusion, that it's
only the exception is when he's involved in a
מצוה. mitzvah. כתב רחמנא וצוה הכהן, ksav Rachmana v'tziva hakohein, that's why
it gets it from the other verse, that the כהן kohein commands
and they clear up the house, to show you even for דבר
רשות dvar reshus you can postpone looking at it. But if it
had said, ואי כתב רחמנא וצוה הכהן, v'ei ksav Rachmana v'tziva hakohein,
if it had just said that, הוי אמינא הני מילי דלאו טומאת
הגוף היא, havi amina hani mili d'lav tumas haguf hi,
I would have said okay, you have discretion by the house, not
for reasons you said that the whole thing is a חידוש, chiddush,
but just because it's not so weighty, it's not your own body,
so maybe there there's more discretion. אבל טומאת הגוף, aval tumas haguf,
but if it's on your body, אימא מיחזי חזי ליה, eima mechezi
chazi lei, maybe there it's something more serious and you have to
see it and you don't have the same discretion. צריכא, tzricha,
so we needed to say both. Now תוספות Tosafot says by saying
both, we don't just say okay for your body, what would רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda say? For your house you have, you don't have
to look at it even for a wide range of discretion, even
for דבר רשות, dvar reshus, even for things that the guy is
not doing a מצוה. mitzvah. For the body the only exception is
when the guy is doing a מצוה. mitzvah. That's what רבי would
say. What's רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda say? רבי says no, you combine
the two. From the case of the house you see you have
general discretion, and from the case of the body you see that
that discretion applies even to the body, so you combine the two
and therefore even when it's a case of טומאה tumah on the
body, you actually the כהן kohein can say even if the guy
isn't doing a מצוה mitzvah and isn't in the middle of like
רגל Regel and wedding, he can choose to wait to look at
it for a time that makes more sense, that's more sympathetic to
the person and his circumstances. Okay, so we will pick up with
this גמרא.